country	year	ref_name	law_no	web	date_leg_pro	date_law	check	date_impl	ref_meas																													
Country	Year	"Reform Name(Legislative Reforms, Administrative Reforms, Attempted Reforms)(English and original language)"	Law Number 	Website if Available	Date of Legislative Proposal (YYYY-MM-DD)	Date of passage into law  (YYYY-MM-DD)	Month-Year automatic check	"Date of implementation/date of entry into force(YYYY-MM-DD)"	Reform measures: For Important Non-Legislative Reforms of Failed Legislative Reforms, Please include notes on timing here, as well-- date of negative vote in parliament, or whatever.  For notes, use a date notation that cannot cause mistakes like 1 Jan 2015 (as opposed to 1.6.2015 which can be June or Jan)- in this column, can you copy in a little of detail from columns, so that this column can be used directly as an illustration in your chapter (see example in next row)	Introduction of Compulsory Public or Statutory  Health Insurance (explain)	Introduction of National Health Service  (explain)	Introduction of Government Mandate to Obtain Health Insurance (explain)	Introduction of new Health Insurance Carriers (Public, Private or Voluntary)  (explain)	Financial, Administrative Support for Health Insurance Carriers? Like government subsidies, tax deductions for payments, regulations on reserves, controls on numbers of sickness funds (Explain)	Changes in financial governance of health insurance, like risk-adjustments, government regulation of contributions, other (explain)	Harmonization/ Fusion of Insurance Schemes? Relationship of Public and Private Health insurance? Explain	Expansion or reduction of Insurance coverage (Number of Persons Covered)? (Explain)	Expansion or Rentrenchment of Health Insurance Benefits Package/ Public Health Service Provision?	Increase or decrease in Co-Payments or Cost-Sharing? (explain)	Cost containment? Caps on Spending?	Changes in Payments to Hospitals? (Explain)	Changes in Payments to Doctors? (Explain)	Changes in system of Quality Control?	Changes in Control of Access to Health System? (Explain)	Measures for Improving / Restricting Access of Migrants to Health System?	Introduction or measures to Support local halth centers (Group ambulatory care)?	Measures to Improve Patients Rights?	Measures to Guarantee Patients' Access to Health Services (e.g., appointment guarantees)?	Privatization of Outpatient care or similar (explain)	Change in ownership of inpatient facilities	Privatization of auxiliary (Supplemental services (Diagnostic, therapies)	Decentralization of Health Services?	Recentralization of Health Services?	Introduction/Restuctions on Private Beds in Public Hospitals? (Explain)	Introduction/Restruction of Private Office Hours in Public Hospitals? (Explain)	Changes to situation of private hospitals/Clinics? (explain) 	privatization measure in pharmacuticla domain	Caps on Pharmceutical expenditure
France	2016	Health system modernisation act - Loi de modernisation de notre système de santé	2016-41	https://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/affichLoiPubliee.do?idDocument=JORFDOLE000029589477&type=general&legislature=14	2014-10-15	2016-01-27	Jan-16		"The law has 227 articles; reinforcement of prevention and health promotion; improvement of access e.g. through generalization of third party-payment in ambulatory care, using set tariffs to pay doctors  directly by SHI; reinforcement of coordinated care e.g. through extension of 'soft gatekeeping'; reinforcment of public hospital sector and regional health agencies ??When was third party payment implemented-- when could one expect a public opinion effect?"	N	N	N	N	n	N	N	N	N	change of payment modalities: set tariffs will be paid directly from SHI to physician	N	"indirect change expected through new definition of ""public hospital service"" i.e. emergency care, teaching, etc."	change of payment modalities: set tariffs will be paid directly from SHI to physician	N	Soft gatekeeping system extend to adolescents, now requiring referral from GPs	N	Yes- professionals are given a new possibility to create local networks or projects concerning specific themes and receive dedicated funding	"Yes- possibility for class action lawsuits; better representation of patients in public agencies "	N	N	N	N	N	N	N	N	"indirect change expected through new definition of ""public hospital service"" including emergency care and teaching activities; it is expected that private hospital will have difficulties meeting eligibility criteria of this service and subsequently suffer a decrease in additional funding (and, potentially, patient flow)"		
France	2014	Social security financing act for 2015 - Loi de financement de la Sécurité sociale pour 2015	2014-1554	https://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/affichTexte.do?cidTexte=JORFTEXT000029953502	2014-10-08	2014-12-22	Dec-14	2015-07-01	Anticipating the generalization of third party-payment in ambulatory care planned for 2017, the present law extends third party payments for beneficiaries of a voucher plan for VHI for low-income groups, if patients follow the gatekeeping treatment pathway. 	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	change of payment modalities: set tariffs will be paid directly from SHI to physician	n	n	change of payment modalities: set tariffs will be paid directly from SHI to physician	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n		
France	2013	Job security act - Loi relative à la sécurisation de l'emploi	2013-504	https://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/affichTexte.do?cidTexte=JORFTEXT000027546648&fastPos=3&fastReqId=943769486&categorieLien=cid&oldAction=rechTexte		2013-06-14	Jun-13	2016-01-01	"All employers are required to offer  group VHI contracts to their employees by January 2016. Out-of-pocket payments expected to decrease as VHI coverage increases; the employer must pay 50% of VHI contributions."	employers are required to offer  group VHI contracts	n	n	n	n	n	n	number of subscribers to VHI expected to rise	n	"out-of-pocket payments expected to decrease as VHI coverage increases; the employer must pay 50% of VHI contributions. "	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n		
France	2011	Social security financing act for 2012 - Loi de financement de la Sécurité sociale pour 2012	2011-1906	https://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/affichTexte.do?cidTexte=JORFTEXT000025005833&categorieLien=id	2011-10-05	2011-12-21	Dec-11	2012-03-01	In light of excessive overbilling by some ambulatory physicians, an optional tariff sector has been introduced in which moderate overbilling (50%) of statutory tariffs is coupled to a reimbursement of the excess sum by VHI. VHI carriers must reimburse the overbilling of the optional tariff sector if they want to receive tax breaks.  Decree in March 2012	n	n	n	n	VHI carriers must reimburse the overbilling of the optional tariff sector if they want to receive tax breaks	n	n	n	n	a decrease in the overall amount of overbilling is expected, but windfall benefits are also expected, in the sense that physicians who do not overbill yet are given an incentive to do so	n	n	volontary capping of overbilling	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n		
France	2009	Hospital, Patient, Health and Territory Act - Loi Hôpital, patient, santé et territoires	2009-879	https://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/affichTexte.do?cidTexte=JORFTEXT000020879475	2008-10-22	2009-07-21	Jul-09	2010-12-31	"The law has 135 articles regrouping four themes. 1) concerning public hospitals, it reinforces of the role of public hospital directors, now holding executive responsibilities previously held by the administrative board; 2) concerning the geographical repartition of ambulatory physicians, night and weekend access and the coordination of different professions has been reinforced; 3) concerning prevention, alcohol sales to minors have been prohibited; 4) concerning the regional organisation of the health system, former regional state and statutory health insurance institutions were merged into Regional Health Agencies. Further: New negative financial incentives in case the patient does not follow the soft-gatekeeping-scheme: the reimbursement of the statutory tariff drops from 70% to 30%. The majority of relevant decrees were emitted over the course of 2010."	N	N	N	N	N	N	N	N	N	Negative financial incentives in case the patient does not follow the soft-gatekeeping-scheme: the reimbursement of the statutory tariff drops from 70% to 30% 	N	N	N	N	N	N	Yes: legal provisions and funding opportunities for multi-professional health centres	"penalisation of physicians that refuse to treat patients in need was set out, but an implementing decree was never issued-in chapter should explain why this situation crops up. (because overbilling not covered by SHI? Yes; Noted for the chapter)"	see before	N	N	N	N	N	N	N	N		
France	2007	Social security financing act for 2008 - Loi de financement de la Sécurité sociale pour 2008	2007-1786	https://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/affichTexte.do?cidTexte=JORFTEXT000017726554	2007-10-11	2007-12-19	Dec-2007	2008-01-01	Extension of deductibles to drugs (€0.5 per package), ancillary care (€0.5 per service) and medical transportation (€2 per transport)	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	new deductible for drugs, ancillary care and transport, annual ceiling of €50	n	n	n	n	n	beneficiaries of state aid for migrant health are exempt from the new deductible	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n		
France	2004	Health insurance act - Loi relative à l'assurance maladie	2004-810	https://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/affichTexte.do?cidTexte=JORFTEXT000000625158&dateTexte=&categorieLien=id	2004-06-16	2004-08-13	Aug-04	2004-12-20	"1) Deductible of €1 is introduced for each consultation, laboratory test and diagnostic imaging; 2) Introduction of a gatekeeping physician, negative financial incentives if gatekeeping physician is not consulted first; 3) Tax break for voluntary health insurance in low-income groups; 4) reform of governance structure, with more executive power for the director of the largest statutory health insurance scheme; 5) creation of the National Health Authority, in charge of evaluation and quality improvement. The majority of relevant decrees were emitted between October and December 2004. The gatekeeping physician scheme is implemented within the scope of the social security financing act for 2005, passing into law on 20 December 2004."	N	N	N	N	N	N	Creation of the National Union of Health Insurance Funds, co-responsible for setting the coverage rate of drugs	Tax break for voluntary health insurance in low-income groups	N	Increased co-payment for hospital stays (from €13, €1 more in 2005, 2006 and 2007), new deductible for consultations	N	N	If a patient does not follow the soft-gatekeeping scheme by consulting a specialist directly, the latter may perform overbilling		N	beneficiaries of state aid for migrant health are exempt from the new deductible	N	N	N	N	N	N	N	N	N	N	N		
France	2003	Social security financing act for 2004 - Loi de financement de la Sécurité sociale pour 2004	2003-1199	https://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/affichTexte.do?cidTexte=JORFTEXT000000249276	2003-10-09	2003-12-18	Dec-2003	2008-12-01	Progressive introduction of DRG system for all public and private hospitals, except psychiatry. ??Start of implementation phase: October 2014, end in 2008-- start in 2004?	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	Introduction of DRGs for all hospitals	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n		
France	1999	Universal health coverage act - Loi portant création d'une couverture maladie universelle	99-641	https://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/affichTexte.do?cidTexte=JORFTEXT000000198392	1999-03-03	2009-07-27	Jul-09	2000-01-01	"Residency-based right to free state coverage for individuals with incomes below a certain level;  it is a social benefit provided by the state, for which a dedicated fund has been created. The scheme offers free basic (statutory) and volontary health insurance. The scheme has replaced existing benefit systems of local administrations. An expansion of coverage is likely, but reliable data is scarce."	Y	N	N	No, it is a social benefit provided by the state, for which a dedicated fund has been created	N	N	The scheme offers free basic (statutory) and volontary health insurance	The scheme has replaced existing benefit systems of local administrations. An expansion of coverage is likely, but reliable data is scarce.	N	N	N	N	The scheme operates only third party payment, care is free at the point of access	N	Free access	Free access	N	N	N	N	N	N	N	N	N	N	N		
France	1996	"The ""Juppé reform"", leading to ordinances - Plan Juppé"	Ordinances 96-344, 96-345, 96-346		1995-11-15	1996-04-25	Apr-96	1996-04-25	"Definition of pluri-annual objectives between the state and statutory health insurance; tightening of regulatory control of physicians with measures of ""medically based cost-containment"", including potential spending caps (caps on spending for ambulatory physicians foreseen, but finally not implemented due to resistance by the profession); creation of a national agency in charge of defining medical norms (increasing ideas and initiatives to have physicians adhere to best practice protocols, but no direct control); creation of regional hospital agencies, consituted by the state and statutory health insurance, responsible for capacity planning, defining quality objectives and allocating funds; an overall reduction of hospital beds (public and private) was wanted and anticipated by decision makers. Annual definition of overspending targets for the social security budget. Increase in tax-based contributions to statutory health insurance; restrictions on reimbursement of specialty drugs; charter for hospital patients rights. Immediate implementation of most articles. The articles introducing spending caps for ambulatory physicians were rejected in a decision of the constitutional council in Decembre 1998 in the context of the social security financing act for 1999.  "	n	n	n	n	n	Increase in tax-based contributions to statutory health insurance	n	n	restrictions on reimbursement of specialty drugs	yes, see before	caps on spending for ambulatory physicians foreseen, but finally not implemented due to resistance by the profession	yearly budget negotiated between hospitals (public and private not-for-profit) and regional hospital agency, based on national budget objectives	caps on spending for ambulatory physicians foreseen, but finally not implemented due to resistance by the profession	indirect: increasing ideas and initiatives to have physicians adhere to best practice protocols, but no direct control	n	n	indirect: provision for pilots of provider networks	charter for hospital patients rights	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	an overall reduction of hospital beds (public and private) was wanted and anticipated by decision makers		
France	1996	Constitutional Act introducing annual legislation on social security finance - Loi constitutionnelle instituant les lois de financement de la sécurité sociale	96-138	https://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/affichTexte.do?cidTexte=JORFTEXT000000741468		1996-02-22	Feb-96	1996-07-23	"estimating receipts of social security bodies for the year to come and setting a growth target for total health care expenditure by statutory health insurance; the annual Act approves the government’s policy directions in health and social security"	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	yearly objectives to be defined	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n		
France	1993	"Act concerning relations between healthcare professions and SHI - Loi relative aux relations entre les professions de santé et l'assurance maladie."	93-8	https://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/affichTexte.do?cidTexte=JORFTEXT000000727115	 	1993-01-04	Jan-93	1993-10-21	"introduction of ceilings for growth in health care expenditure; mandatory practice guidelines ; a basis for the coding of medical procedures and of diagnoses; creation of regional unions of self-employed doctors (participation in health care system analysis, quality improvement and health promotion, with little short-term tangible effects). Collective agreements between SHI and physicians of 21 October 1993: ceilings for expenditure growth, mandatory guidelines."	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	yes, growth ceilings for health expenditure, which could however be overrun. 	n	n	increased formal implications of regional physicians in quality monitoring, with little short-term tangible effects	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n		
France	1991	Hospital reform act - Loi portant réforme hospitalière	91-748	https://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/affichTexte.do?cidTexte=JORFTEXT000000720668		1991-07-31	Jul-91	1991-07-31	Regional health organization plans as tool for capacity planning for public and private hospitals. Multi-annual plans are being signed between SHI, the State, local authorities and hospitals, and the authorisations for new beds must respect these plans. 	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n		
France	1990	Financing law for 1991 - Loi de finances pour 1991	90-1168	https://www.legifrance.gouv.fr/affichTexte.do?cidTexte=JORFTEXT000000717191&dateTexte=19901230	 	1990-12-29	Jan 00	1991-02-01	Introduction of the General Social Contribution to enlarge the social security financing base,  over the years (main rise until 2000), it will become more and more important. 	n	n	n	n	n	"introduction of a general earmarked tax based on total income as an addition to employer's and employee's contributions to SHI; over the years (main rise until 2000), it will become more and more important.  "	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n	n		